Guide to the Farrar Family Papers, 1740-1984 and undated (bulk 1878-1940)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Farrar Family papers 1740-1984 and undated (bulk 1878-1940)
Farrar family
9 linear feet Extent: 5000 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.00382
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Farrar Family Papers was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1975-1976.
Biographical Note
Preston C. Farrar was an English teacher at Allegheny High School, PA, and in New York City. He was also a professor at the University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, NC.
Collection Overview
Chiefly family and professional correspondence, but also printed material, writings and speeches, scrapbooks, diaries, clippings, and photographs. The collection primarily pertains to the Farrar family and to Preston C. Farrar. Much of the Correspondence Series (1801-1976, undated) consists of personal letters among family members, especially written to Preston C. Farrar; his wife Edna P. Farrar; brother Samuel Clark Farrar, Jr.; sister Josephine; father Samuel Clark Farrar; and mother Ettie Farrar. However, the series also documents the careers in education of Samuel Farrar, Sr., and Preston Farrar. Business letters from Samuel Farrar concern real estate investments in Pennsylvania and New York that father and son owned jointly.
The Diaries Series (1887-1927, undated) includes diaries Preston C. Farrar kept while attending Washington and Jefferson College (1887-1891). The Writings and Speeches Series (1890-1925, undated) includes writings by Preston C. Farrar on teaching literature, English, and education. The Printed Material Series (1878-1957) includes drama and opera programs for New York City theaters, collected by Edith P. Farrar (1899-1957). The Photographs Series contains pictures and photograph albums primarily of family and friends (1888-1938, undated). The Scrapbooks and Clippings Series (1879-1945, undated) contains items that pertain to educational law and school operation; family events; local Allegheny elections; and world news, especially World War I. The Genealogy Series (1740-1984, undated) contains primarily correspondence, notes, and transcripts of wills relating to the Cooke/Cook family.
Subject Headings
Farrar, Preston C.; Farrar, Samuel Clark; University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill -- Faculty; Washington and Jefferson College (Washington, Pa.); Real estate investment -- Pennsylvania; Real estate investment -- New York (State); English teachers -- Pennsylvania -- Correspondence; Educational law and legislation; Theater -- New York (State) -- New York -- History; Educators -- Correspondence; Education, Secondary -- Pennsyvania -- History; Education, Secondary -- New York -- History; Education, Higher; Literature -- Study and teaching (Secondary); Literature -- Study and teaching (Higher); Elections -- Pennsylvania; Speeches; Scrapbooks; Photographs; Diaries; Clippings
Contents of Collection
- Diaries Series, 1887-1927 and undated
  Includes the diaries Preston C. Farrar kept while attending Washington and Jefferson College from 1887-1891.
  - 1887-1894 (Box 1)
  - 1896-1918 (Box 1)
  - 1922-1927, undated (Box 1)
  - undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence Series, 1801-1976 and undated
  Primarily consists of family letters, especially written to Preston C. Farrar; his wife Edna P. Farrar; brother Samuel Clark Farrar, Jr.; sister Josephine; father Samuel Clark Farrar; and mother Ettie Farrar. Series also documents the careers in education of Samuel Farrar, Sr., and Preston Farrar. Business letters from Samuel Farrar concern real estate investments in Pennsylvania and New York that father and son held in joint ownership.
  - 1801-1886 (Box 1)
  - 1887 (Box 1)
  - 1888 (Box 1)
  - 1890 (Box 2)
  - 1889 (Box 2)
  - 1891
    - January-April (Box 2)
    - May-August (Box 2)
    - September-December (Box 2)
  - 1892 (Box 2)
  - 1893
    - January-July (Box 2)
    - August-December (Box 2)
  - 1894 (Box 3)
  - 1895-1896 (Box 3)
  - 1897
    - January-August (Box 3)
    - September-December (Box 3)
  - 1898
    - January-March (Box 3)
    - April-June (Box 3)
    - July-December (Box 3)
  - 1899 (Box 4)
  - [1800s] undated (Box 4)
  - 1900 (Box 4)
  - 1901
    - January-February (Box 4)
    - March-April (Box 4)
    - May-June (Box 4)
    - July-October (Box 4)
    - November-December (Box 5)
  - 1902
    - January-April (Box 5)
    - May-June (Box 5)
    - July-December (Box 5)
  - 1903 (Box 5)
  - 1904 (Box 5)
  - 1905 (Box 5)
  - 1906 (Box 5)
  - 1907-1908 (Box 6)
  - 1910-1911 (Box 6)
  - 1912-1913 (Box 6)
  - 1914-1915 (Box 6)
  - 1916
    - January-August (Box 6)
    - September-December (Box 6)
  - 1917-1923 (Box 6)
  - 1924 (Box 6)
  - 1925 (Box 7)
  - 1925 (Box 7)
  - 1926 (Box 7)
  - 1927
    - January-June (Box 7)
    - July (Box 7)
    - August-September (Box 7)
    - October-December (Box 7)
  - 1928
    - January-February (Box 7)
    - March-April (Box 7)
    - May-June (Box 8)
    - July-October (Box 8)
    - November-December (Box 8)
  - 1929
    - January-February (Box 8)
    - March-May (Box 8)
    - June-July (Box 8)
    - August (Box 8)
    - September-October (Box 9)
    - November-December (Box 9)
  - 1930
    - January-February (Box 9)
    - March-November (Box 9)
    - December (Box 9)
  - 1931 (Box 9)
  - 1932
    - January-August (Box 9)
    - September-December (Box 9)
  - 1933 (Box 10)
    - January-March (Box 10)
    - April-December (Box 10)
  - 1934 (Box 10)
  - 1935
    - January-March (Box 10)
    - April-May (Box 10)
    - June-October (Box 10)
    - November-December (Box 10)
  - 1936 (Box 10)
  - 1937
    - January-November (Box 10)
    - December (Box 11)
  - 1938
    - January-August (Box 11)
    - December (Box 11)
  - 1939
    - January-August (Box 11)
    - September-December (Box 11)
  - 1940
    - January-November (Box 11)
    - December (Box 11)
  - 1941 (Box 12)
    - January-August (Box 12)
    - September-December (Box 12)
  - 1942
    - January-October (Box 12)
    - November-December (Box 12)
  - 1943 (Box 12)
  - 1944
    - January-June (Box 12)
    - July-December (Box 12)
  - 1945 (Box 12)
  - 1946-1949 (Box 13)
  - 1950 (Box 13)
  - 1951-1953 (Box 13)
  - 1954-1976 (Box 13)
  - undated, (5 folders) (Box 13)
- Writings and Speeches, 1890-1925 and undated
  Includes writings by Preston C. Farrar on teaching literature, English, and education.
  - 1890-1925, undated (Box 14)
  - Untitled Manuscripts, undated
    - Chapters I-IX (Box 14)
    - Chapters X-XV (Box 14)
    - Chapters XVI-XXI (Box 14)
    - Notes, (2 folders) (Box 15)
- Printed Material, 1878-1957 and undated
  Includes drama and opera programs for New York City theaters, collected by Edith P. Farrar, 1899-1957.
  - General
    - 1878-1896 (Box 15)
    - 1897-1919 (Box 15)
    - 1923-1929 (Box 15)
    - undated (Box 15)
  - Drama and Opera Programs
    - 1899-1929 (Box 16)
    - 1929
      - November-December (Box 16)
    - 1930 (Box 16)
    - 1931
      - January-November 2 (Box 16)
      - November 9-December (Box 16)
    - 1932
      - January-May (Box 16)
      - June-December (Box 16)
    - 1933
      - January-March (Box 16)
      - April-June (Box 17)
    - 1934-1957 (Box 17)
    - undated, (2 folders) (Box 17)
- Photographs Series, 1888-1938 and undated
  Contains pictures and photograph albums primarily of family and friends.
  - 1888-1931 (Box 17)
  - undated, (2 folders) (Box 17-18)
- Scrapbooks, and Clippings Series, 1879-1945 and undated
  Contains items that pertain to educational law and school operation; family events; local Allegheny elections; and world news, especially World War I.
  - Scrapbooks Subseries, 1879-1930
    - Photocopies from Album 1, 1879-1897 (Box 18)
    - Photocopies from Album 2, 1914 (Box 18)
    - Photocopies from Album 3, 1914, (2 folders) (Box 18)
    - Album 4, 1900-1930 (Box 18)
  - Clippings Subseries, 1886-1945 and undated
    - 1886-1905 (Box 18)
    - 1907-1924 (Box 18)
    - 1928-1945, undated (Box 18)
- Genealogy Series, 1740-1984 and undated
  - 1740-1943 (Box 19)
  - 1952-1984, undated (Box 19)
- Miscellaneous Series, 1887-1968 and undated
  - Construction of CCC Camp SES-1, 1935 (Box 19)
  - Houseplans, 1928 July-1935 August and undated, Rocky Ridge Rd., Chapel Hill, NC, (3 folders) (Box 19)
  - Legal Papers, 1893-1948, undated (Box 19)
  - Playreaders Group, [Dramatic Club of Chapel Hill High School], 1935 (Box 19)
  - 1887-1911 (Box 20)
  - 1912-1968 (Box 20)
  - undated (Box 20)
- Clippings and Scrapbooks Series
  - Scrapbooks Subseries
    - Album 1, 1879-1897 (Box 21)
    - Album 2, 1914 (Box 21)
    - Album 3, 1914 (Box 21)
- Oversize boxes
  - Photographs Series, undated
    - Photograph albums, undated ([ca. 1880s]-[ca. 1920s]), (3 albums) (Box 22)
    - Loose photographs, undated (Box 23)
    - Photograph albums, undated ([ca. 1880s]-[ca. 1920s]), (2 albums) (Box 23)
    - Loose photographs, 1928; 1938; and undated (Box 24)
      Includes the Wellesley College senior class picture for 1928 and the 30th reunion picture of the class of 1898.
  - Clippings and Scrabooks Series
    - Clippings Subseries
      - Clippings, 1896-1929 (Box 24)
        Includes clippings about Elizabeth Dean Farrar.
    - Scrapbooks Subseries
      - Photocopies of pages from Album 1 (Box 24)
      - Photocopies of pages from Album 2 (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous Series
    - 1912-1968 (Box 24)
- Oversize folders
  - Photographs series, 1915
    - Co. I, Plattsburg, first Provisional Regiment at Military Instruction Camp, (2 photographs) (Opaperfolder 1)
      Photographs include a group shot of the men and a location shot of the camp.
  - Clippings Series, 1858-1945
    - Clippings (Opaperfolder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Series, 1935
    - CCC Camp SES-1, 1935 (Opaperfolder 1)